<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-21T20:23:01+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Passpartout</title><subtitle>Travel Blog to document our trip across the world  and all the encounters that come along.
</subtitle><author><name>Passpartout</name></author><entry><title type="html">Searching Solitude on Flinders</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Flinders/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Searching Solitude on Flinders" /><published>2020-02-17T22:38:53+08:00</published><updated>2020-02-17T22:38:53+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Flinders</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Flinders/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-1-2020-feb-17&quot;&gt;Day 1: 2020-Feb-17&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a reset today. We are isolated from the rest of the world on Flinders island and the weather is well on its way to achieve 40 to 80 mm of precipitation, which is more than the average rainfall for February, the driest month on the island. For reference the average annual precipitation is 839 mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idea to visit Flinders island has been a captivating one considering the isolation of the area and challenges to get here. The island also boasts some of the most beautiful beaches in Tasmania, great wildlife, birdwatching and history. Flinders is the largest and the main island of the Furneaux islands group. 12000 years ago it was part of the Bassian Plain which served as a land bridge between the mainland Australia and Tasmania. With the end of the ice age the water levels raised and flooded parts of the Plain which is now constitutes the Bass Strait. 
With no land connection between neither Tasmania nor mainland Australia, Flinders is cut-off from both and the only way to get to the island is by air, serviced by Sharp Airlines, and a more off-the-beaten path cargo barge serviced by the Furneaux group ferry. For economical and logistical reasons we decided to take a barge to the island and fly out. Barge in itself has been an interesting experience and perhaps worth skipping the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forecast was favorable at the time of booking the trip to Flinders with sunny weather and mostly cleared skies. Two days before our departure it changed drastically. For the only two days when we were supposed to be on the island we now expected heavy rain with the rest of the days before and after the trip sunny and clear. Tasmania once again proved that its weather is difficult to predict and any forecast more than two days away is not reliable. To make things worse, Flinders
is located on 40° south, a zone known as the Roaring Forties. It’s right in the wind corridor, a perfect place for wind turbines but less hospitable for picky tourists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barge. We planned to drop our rental car in Launceston and catch a 1-hr bus ride to the ferry terminal located in Bridgeport. In the morning I received an email asking whether we still planned to travel by barge and call the office to make the payment. The office closes at 4:30 pm while the barge departs at low tide with no guarantee departure due to unreliable weather. Once we dropped the car in the airport we called the office to process the payment. We were still determined to travel and make the most of the trip. Who knows… maybe the weather would prove better than expected. Launceston airport has been recently renovated with modern facilities and luggage storage. Uber pick-up zone is clearly marked at the airport. We took Uber to the bus stopped. A single bus ride per day is scheduled between Launceston and Bridgeport, perhaps due to the lack of the demand. We confirmed the schedule and the bus number and set to patiently wait for its arrival. An empty bus with no number pulled in right after we arrived. It was quite ahead of schedule for our bus and we continued to wait. The bus left, and we continued to wait. We started to be concerned after about 10 minutes passed after expected bus ETA. It was time to call the transit system. We only had 2.5 hr left before the ferry departure. The lady on the phone told us that the bus has already departed and was well on its way to the destination (?!) As it appeared the bus without a number was our bus, the only scheduled bus to Bridgeport. We tried to hitchhike for 20 minutes but running out of time turned back to Uber. Someone did decide to Uber us to Bridgeport. There was not a single car on the road until we reached Bridgeport. Probably not the easiest town to hitchhike in the low season. We made it to the ferry 20 minutes ahead of time, sufficient time to get dinner at the low-key cafe right by the terminal. They offer local seafood, smoothies and other expected miscellaneous such us pastries, burgers, coffee. At 6:30 pm we were on our way to the barge. Even though we knew this was a cargo barge, we were still surprised how much it lived up to its purpose. The barge can take up to 12 passengers and there is only seating area in the bottom section of the boat with no windows and access to fresh air. The hope to see a whale or an albatross quickly vanished. No one asked for our tickets, identification and provided no safety briefing before the departure. There were 5 passengers including us apart from the regular crew on the boat: an older man whose truck would not start and the crew member was trying to help him fix it and a couple traveling for two weeks to Flinders in the camper-van with a dog. Otherwise, there were cars, boats, cement making machine, sacks with cement, animal craters, animals and a farm spirit. Seating area had a broken TV, a row of working rain-boots, dirty uniforms and us. After some time contemplating why it takes 8 hours for the barge to travel 120 km (it’s a 25 min flight from Launceston) and how to make it through the night I fell asleep on one of the benches. I woke up when we finally arrived to the port of Lady sensing the changes in the boat movement or, perhaps, eagerly anticipating the arrival. It was 4:09 am and luckily we had a rental car dropped off at the port waiting for us. It is vital to have the drop-off arranged ahead of time if traveling by the barge as there is nothing within the walking distance to the port. I doubt anyone on the boat had noticed that we left. I wholeheartedly believe that someone from the crew would have woken us up but I would not count on it. We decided to sleep for a few hours in the nearest campground - Yellow Beach campground. When we arrived there was only one camper-van parked. Yellow Beach is a beautiful spot for camping with clean facilities, rain shelter, BBQ and a nice scenic beach. The sky was clear and due to low light pollution we were treated to a beautiful night sky. When we woke up the camper-van had already left and we were the only ones on the campground. The morning was sunny and warm, however windy. We could see clouds starting to form. After a morning stroll on the beach and greetings from a wallaby jumping by we headed to the visitor center. Being a low tourist season and 8 hours barge ride away from Tasmania we were the only ones in the visitor center and got well deserved personalized attention. The lady in the visitor center checked the weather forecast, suggested a campground with the shelter from the rain and things to do on the island during the wet weather. There were no much going on. The biggest offering of the island is the famed Strzelescki National Park and beaches. Taking advantage of the window of the warm and clear skies we decided to do Trousers point circuit in Strzelescki national park. It’s a beautiful 1.9 km walking track showcasing the coastal shrubs, granite rock formations covered in red lichen, white sand beach, vast views on Strzlescki peak which we hope to climb the next day. On our walk we had multiple sightings of green rosella (a parrot species endemic to Tasmania and Bass Strait islands), tiny and curious blue wren, wallaby, and echidna. At the end of the short walk we found ourselves on the picturesque beach overlooking Fotgeringate bay in complete solitude, a perfect spot to have a lunch picnic. It doesn’t get better than that and we would have stayed much longer enjoying the clear turquoise waters of the bay and chirping of the wrens occasionally interrupted by gurgles and whistles of a curravong, however the dark clouds moving towards us signaled that it was time to look for a shelter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oksana Protsukha</name></author><category term="Australia" /><category term="Tasmania" /><summary type="html">Day 1: 2020-Feb-17</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diving in the Great Barrier Reef</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Cairns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diving in the Great Barrier Reef" /><published>2020-02-08T22:38:53+08:00</published><updated>2020-02-08T22:38:53+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Cairns</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Cairns/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-1-2020-feb-06&quot;&gt;Day 1: 2020-Feb-06&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made an opportunistic decision to come diving at GBR during our walk in Akaroa, a little quaint town known for its French heritage, on our last day in New Zealand. All we had booked for our trip in Australia at the time was our flight to Brisbane and one week later a flight from Sydney to Hobart. We had a vague idea of what to do in between. Great Barrier Reef seemed like a place not to be missed considering the grave forecast that it might disappear by 2050. 
With a quick google search we realized that Great Barrier Reef is bigger than BIG and, that Cairns, the best town from which to explore the reef was several hours flight away from Brisbane. We knew it was the largest coral reef structure in the world, however, the fact that its area stretches 2300 km off the Australian Eastern coastline and spans 344,400 sq. km still came as a surprise. To put into perspective, Great Barrier Reef is roughly the size of 70 million football fields or the the same area as Japan, Germany, Malaysia or Italy combined. Luckily, the flights were available and most importantly affordable.
With minimal preparation we embarked on the journey. This time we skipped all our usual checks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latest weather forecast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diving tour options and availability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Periods of high and low seasons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nico booked the flight on Feb 5th and I booked a hostel from Feb-6 to Feb-9 to make sure we would have a place to stay upon our arrival…
We arrived past midnight on Feb 6th and got to our hostel shortly after 1 am. The host opened the door and asked if we had booked our stay since he didn’t expect anyone checking in that night?! It took few minutes of confusion for me to realize that I miscalculated our check-in time. Luckily our half-asleep and confused host was able to find an empty room for us (after unsuccessfully verifying that “our room” was empty… oops). 
After few hours of sleep and still half dreaming, we went to hunt for an overnight boat tour to GBR. It didn’t take long to get a reminder that we were in Australis. Few meters from our hostel and right in the touristy center of the town we stumbled upon a big tree with a colony of flying foxes. The creatures were restlessly hanging from all over the tree. No one seemed to care about our discovery. People were going about their daily lives without showing a slight interest in the colony. After ten minutes of staring at the flying foxes, we continued on our quest to sign up for the boat tour. 
Multiple visitor centers and overwhelming amount of options didn’t make things easy. As we discovered there was no official or state-run visitor center and most centers were not locally owned. As it turned out, this was a low or rainy season at Cairns with very few tourists and booking a tour was a breeze. We finally settled on booking an overnight boat tour with a local tour agency who promised us the best experience for the best price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/GBRFlyingFoxes.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/GBRFlyingFoxes.jpeg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/GBRFlyingFoxes.jpeg 800w,            /assets/resized/1400/GBRFlyingFoxes.jpeg 1400w,    &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Flying Foxes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-2-feb-7-2020&quot;&gt;Day 2: Feb-7-2020&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 7 am we boarded the boat of Reef Encounters. Among people who were on the boat were those who were going on a day dive and those staying overnight and longer. After breakfast and filling our all the paperwork, we got a detailed rundown of our day schedule. Day boat brings overnight passengers to an agreed upon dive site where it picks up the divers to were scheduled to go back to Cairns and drops off the new batch of divers. Overnight passengers then enjoy two day dives and one night dive following by three more dives the following day or more if they stay more than one night on the boat. Those who purchased a five-dives prepaid package and are new to diving are usually surprised to learn that the actual number of dives is usually restricted by their flight schedule. Neither night dive was not included in the package. To avoid being disappointed it’s important to do the homework ahead of time. We didn’t. However, we didn’t purchase a prepaid package either. After talking to the instructor and divemasters on the boat we were persuaded that the night dive was a must. How could we miss the chance to swim with sharks and groupers, who were told to be in the big numbers during the dive attracted by the torch light?
We had to do the night dive as a prerequisite. Warm water and multitude of colorful reefs and marine life made it very easy to enjoy the experience and triggered the desire for more. It is an addictive activity. The more experience you gain, the more you want to dive. It is also special in that it is built upon common sense and defiance of gravity. 
Colorful corals and beautiful harmless fish during the day transformed into dark grayish void filled with big harmless fish searching for food at night: sharks (white, black-tip and gray reef sharks), cod, giant trevally and others. They were following human divers with torch lights lazily looking for food illuminated by curious us. Surprisingly yet, with a touch of light the corals are as a vivid and more as during the day. It .would have been a more fulfilling experience if I were comfortable to dive independently. Perhaps an Advance Open Water Diver certification?..
Stunning views today and unforgettable experience snorkeling and diving. We decided to do a 6:30 morning dive the next day and two sessions of snorkeling. Not only we were limited by our upcoming flight the following day but try-dives were fairly expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/GBRShark.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/GBRShark.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/GBRShark.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1400/GBRShark.jpg 1400w,    &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Whitetip reef shark&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-3-feb-8-2020&quot;&gt;Day 3: Feb-8￼-2020&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up right before the sunrise and made our way to the upper deck to see the first morning sun. The sky was in full morning glory sprinkled with patches of yellow and pink. Brown booby was relaxing on the boat rail and enjoying the serenity of the morning. He looked at me with little curiosity and let me come close enough to say hello. Spotting boobies in a wild is always magical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/GBRSunrise.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/GBRSunrise.jpeg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/GBRSunrise.jpeg 800w,            /assets/resized/1400/GBRSunrise.jpeg 1400w,    &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sunrise on Great Barrier Reef&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few minutes later it was time for a morning dive at The Fingers. It’s a magical time to be in the water. Little colorful fish just woken up start feeding and playing in the corals while sharks and their other nocturnal friends have not yet fallen asleep. The water is crystal clear blue, morning sunshine penetrates the depth of the water, the temperature is pleasant and enjoyable to the body. 
We put our diving gear on and got ready for our last dive. Tomorrow we are flying to Brisbane and no diving is allowed 24 hours before the flight to avoid potentially fatal Decompression sickness disease (DCD). The schools of fish and lonely adventurers surrounded us from all sides: trout, sweetlips, parrotfish, butterfly fish, cardinal fish. They mostly seemed to be ignorant of us and continued their breakfast followed by hide and seek game. At times I had an indispensable desire to be part of the school, to attract their attention, to have them play with me… in vain. The colors of the corals ranged from ionic teal to deep purple to orange to pink, making up every single color and more of the color pallet in a modern paint shop. They resembled a fairytale like garden from Alice of the Wonderland. White-tip reef shark seemingly asleep woke up and started scanning for the last final meal of the day. She did not care much about us, divers. Few minutes later eel in a mesmerizing serpentine movement swam below me. Seeing the creature in the water is absolutely stunning. We continued swimming with the multitude of fish among the corals very carefully not to disturb their world. Corals are slow growing and long-lived sea animals. They grow only meager few inches per year, and even a slight damage means years of growth lost. If left not damaged they can greet visitors for the next 800 years! When you get to know them you want to protect them and their fragile ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/GBRNicoFishSchool.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/GBRNicoFishSchool.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/GBRNicoFishSchool.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1400/GBRNicoFishSchool.jpg 1400w,    &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Swimming with the school of snapper at Twin Peaks&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we have two more snorkeling sessions and then back to land full of tropical birds and flying-foxes. 
For the final snorkeling sessions the boat relocated to the Twin Peaks area. The name triggered nostalgic emotions of being away from home. Great Barrier Reef’s Twins Peaks as its, likely more famous San Francisco cousins, did not disappoint. There we spotted a curious and timid clown fish picking from its coral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last snorkeling session was quite short as we were about to transfer to the day boat for our return trip to Cairns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overnight reef tours are run in a fairly ingenious way and highly flexible way. One can stay as many days as they wish on the boat, provided there is an availability. Daily the day boat drops-off and picks up the passengers. The overnight boat offers a hostee program, which can be a great bargain for young travelers with time and little budget to stay on the boat longer. Any passenger who stays on a boat as a customer for the first night can become a hostee for the consequent one to several nights. A hostee helps with routing boat upkeep like washing the dishes, doing laundry and etc. and in return he or she can stay without a charge and enjoy at minimum one dive per day. Those lucky few who visiting during the low season and calm sunny weather get the most of the offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once back in Cairns we spent some time exploring the galleries that featured aboriginal arts. Northern Queensland has a sizable aboriginal community 4.4% (221,400 as of 2018) and is a great place to learn more about the First Nations people of Australia. 
I wish we had more time to explore and learn. In the evening we headed back to the flying foxes colony. Being nocturnal, they fly away in search for food with the sunset. Looking closely in the binoculars we could see them waking up, spreading the wings, jumping between the branches. Around 6 pm the first foxes started to fly away. As the sun was getting lower more foxes were up in the sky, at first circling around the tree and then flying away into the city and into the void of the horizon. With sunset the sky was turning darker more so from the thousands of flying foxes rather than the lack of light. The full moon amplified the surreality of the scenery and elevated the feelings of superiority of the nature over humans. It was, perhaps, the most majestic manifestation of the power of nature I have experienced so far on our trip. The creatures, however, incredible and mesmerizing to watch, are loud and contribute to pollution of the water tanks with drinking water. It is no wonder that they get a lot of complaints from the locals. Yet, they are an important element of the local eco-system and serve as  principal pollinators of variety of plants. Without them the eco-system might not survive. I hope flying foxes continue their symbiotic relationship with the residents and tourists alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Useful links:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://reefencounter.com.au/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Reef Encounters&lt;/a&gt;: we loved our diving experience with this company. It’s locally owned and offers different rate options.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.padi.com/courses/open-water-diver/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PADI&lt;/a&gt;: though try diving has been an amazing experience, I highly recommend getting certified. The experience is exponantially better if you are comfortable under the water and much more affordable.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freedomhostels.com/cairns/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Freedom Hostels Cairns&lt;/a&gt;: is centrally located and deluxe rooms are quite nice. Basic windowless option is somewhat meh.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://cafnec.org.au/wildlife-issues/bats/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spectacled Flying-Foxes&lt;/a&gt;: these special creatures deserve few minutes of an additional read.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oksana Protsukha</name></author><category term="Australia" /><summary type="html">Day 1: 2020-Feb-06</summary></entry></feed>